PORFIRIO BASALDUA

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

PROFILE

An experienced software engineer with more than 6 years serving in development and leadership roles, worked on distributed, scalable and resilient cloud-native systems. Looking to apply this expertise to the field of Machine Learning, take on new challenges and make meaningful contributions as part of a crossfunctional team.

CONTACT INFORMATION

Phone: (+52) 55 65 08 37 22 Email: porfirioBasaldua@gmail.com LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/basporfirio

CERTIFICATIONS

April 2023. AWS Machine Learning Engineer (Udacity).

December 2021. Professional Cloud Architect - Google Cloud Platform

SKILLS

Soft skills

- Active listening.
- Effective communication.
- Leadership.
- Coaching.
- Teamwork.
- Collaboration.
- · Critical thinking.

Programming and tools

- Python (Advanced).
- SQL (Advanced).
- Sci-kit learn (Advanced).
- Pandas (Advanced).
- PyTorch (Intermediate).
- Numpy (Intermediate).
- Architecting in the cloud (Intermediate).
- AWS Sagemaker (Intermediate).
- AWS Lambda (Intermediate).
- AWS S3 (Intermediate).
- AWS EC2 (Intermediate).

Languages

- English (Advanced).
- Spanish (Native).

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Lead Software Engineer

IBM (consultant through Persistent Systems) December 2022 - Present

- Estimate the probability of survival of oncology patients with Machine Learning estimator.
- Create pipelines to automate testing and deployment, using Infrastructure as Code and other DevOps automation tools.
- Configure and run manual as well as automated tests.
- Develop, test and maintain public APIs for IBM's clients.

Technical Lead

Vexi

January 2021 - December 2022

- Managed a virtual team of 7 engineers distributed across 3 states, adopted SCRUM methodology for project management.
- Served as a point of contact for external stakeholders and other team leaders, collaborating on project advancements as well as coordinating dependencies.
- Recruited and trained 3 engineers who still contribute to the enterprise.
- Redesigned monolithic applications as microservices and APIs.
- Moved workloads to multicloud environment.
- Mentored junior developers to solve challenging technical issues.

Relevant projects:

- Constructed Machine Learning system to estimate probability of debt repayment.
- Upgraded back-end services from Python 2.7 to Python 3.8.
- Developed new system for the Collections department.

Full Stack Developer

Vexi

February 2018 - December 2020

- Gathered, analyzed and helped implement requirements for web applications, working with technologies across the technology stack.
- Introduced SQL queries and reports that allowed business managers to monitor key metrics for their processes.
- Improved code quality by writing unit tests for new and existing code.

Relevant projects:

- Created connection to AMEX network.
- Overhauled Accounting system.
- Built Customer Satisfaction modules for in-house ERP.

EDUCATION

Monterrey Institute of Technology and Higher Education

Bachelor of Science in Robotics and Digital Systems, August 2012 - December 2016

- Graduated with honors.
- Score of 90 / 100.
- · Volunteer for student association.